<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
<method></method>

Overview
A level 2 HAZUS MH MR3 study was completed for this project	 which incorporated updated building information. In order to calculate loss due to flooding	 HAZUS requires the following information about the built environment: structure location	 occupancy type	 square footage	 first floor height above grade	 as well as replacement and content values. All but content value and first floor height above grade were available in King County’s standard GIS data package.  This package dated April 2009	 includes parcels	 assessment information	 and essential facilities.  The improvement value from King County’s Assessor was used for the replacement value. Content value and first floor height above grade were not available for this study area and were calculated using HAZUS default methodologies (see Links).  King County did not include the necessary transportation and utility data required for HAZUS	 so the default values were used.

Prior to incorporation into HAZUS	 data provided by King County was formatted to work within the Comprehensive Data Management System (CDMS)	 a tool provided by FEMA to incorporate localized data into HAZUS. Detailed methodologies and assumptions for each of the GIS layers are provided in the sections to follow. Calculations	 fields	 and tables used are provided in Appendix A.

In addition to local GIS data	 HAZUS uses flood depth grids to calculate economic losses. Depth grids are created from hydrologic and hydraulic modeling	 which show flood depth in feet.  For this study	 three depth grids were used including the USACE 17	600 cfs (Scenario 1)	 the King County 100 year base flood study (Scenario 2)	 and a combination of both studies with 17	600 cfs with levee removals (Scenario 3). Using the combination of the depth grid and the local data	 HAZUS calculates economic losses	 shelter requirements	 and debris.  A comparison was also completed between each flood scenario.

Methods
The database construction was completed using Microsoft Access. The creation of the tables required many queries	 calculations	 and joining in order for the information to be formatted correctly for HAZUS (see Appendix).  Once the data was in the correct format it was imported into CDMS which updates the statewide dataset (originally given with HAZUS). The parcel data was input as aggregated data by census block. Once input into CDMS	 fields are chosen to match the HAZUS fields such as replacement value. Once completed	 the existing state dataset was updated with the information for the locality given (i.e. King County). The statewide dataset was only updated locally to the user’s computer; therefore	 the dataset would need to be copied to other computers or a network to be used for future HAZUS analyses. Once this process was completed the updated HAZUS inventory was available in HAZUS.

HAZUS allows the user to input a depth grid which is used to calculate economic losses and damages. A study region was created in HAZUS by census blocks	 the smallest unit of analysis. Census blocks were chosen based on the extent of the Green River Valley.  Once HAZUS created the study region	 the food hazard type was set to riverine. The depth grid was supplied under User data and a new scenario was created.  Once the floodplain was delineated	 the analysis was run for general building stock	 shelter requirements and debris.  HAZUS found no bridge	 utility	 or agriculture losses using the original HAZUS inventory data.  This information could be updated with local data to better determine these losses.

HAZUS then outputs the results in tables or reports	 and also maps the data which can then be exported into an ArcGIS format. The data was mapped for total economic loss	 substantial damage	 shelters	 and debris.  The maps shown in this report were created from this output.

HAZUS Data Assumptions and Damage Estimates
For residential occupancy	 HAZUS calculates the content value to be 50% of the building cost. For all other occupancies the building value could be multiplied by 50-150% to determine content value (see HAZUS Technical Manuals).  These estimates could significantly affect the total economic loss	 especially since the Green River valley contains large warehousing facilities.  To better constrain the content and inventory values	 the appropriate data should be supplied and input into HAZUS.

The previous calculations refer only to the inventory base data	 not the calculated losses. To calculate losses	 HAZUS-MH uses depth damage curves.  Depth-damage curves are contained in HAZUS-MH and come from various data sources. For each census block an appropriate damage curve is assigned for each occupancy type and water depths are used to determine the associated percent damage. The percent damage is multiplied by the replacement value (i.e. building value	 content value etc.) to determine the full dollar loss. Shelter estimations are determined based on flood depth	 individuals or households within a census block	 population of a census block	 number of census blocks affected	 and restricted ingress/egress areas due to flooding. Updated demographic information was not provided by King County; therefore data from the 2000 Census was used. The shelter estimations are believed to be a minimum due to population changes in the area since 2000.  Debris is calculated based on flood depth and calculates debris generated from buildings and contents	 not roads or utilities. More information on the HAZUS-MH calculations and depth curves can be found in the HAZUS User and Technical Manuals (See Links).
</metadata>
